Since 2003, a special type of scam targeting the elderly
Od roku 2003 w Japonii króluje biorące na cel osoby starsze
called the money transfer scam has proliferated in Japan.
oszustwo zwane „przekrętem na przelew”.
Financial damages increased every year, reaching 56.5 billion yen in 2014.
Straty finansowe rosną z roku na rok. W 2014 r. wynosiły 56,5 miliarda jenów.
Now, in 2019, scammers have changed their techniques,
W 2019 roku oszuści zmienili metody,
and the damage continues.
w dalszym ciągu okradając obywateli.
-I'll do anything! -There it is! "I'll do anything!"
- Zrobię wszystko! - No proszę, wszystko!
I'll give you the answer. They're in the scamming business as well.
Powiem ci. Też siedzą w przekrętach.
But they're not looking for a lackey.
Ale nie szukają pomagiera.
You'll be scamming old people over the phone.
Będziesz ściemniał dziadków przez telefon.
Time for you to see some real action!
Czas na prawdziwą zabawę!
EPISODE 2
ODCINEK 2
What have you done, Mom? We're talking about 20 million yen!
Co mama narobiła? To 20 milionów jenów!
You should have known that something fishy was going on!
Przecież to śmierdziało na kilometr!
Can you not even recognize your son's voice over the phone?
Nie poznałaś głosu syna?
Are you going senile?
Odbija ci na starość?
This is the third case this month.
To trzeci raz w tym miesiącu.
Bastards.
Dranie.
FIRST DAY OF TRAINING
PIERWSZY DZIEŃ SZKOLENIA
INVESTMENT REAL ESTATE SCRIPT
SCENARIUSZ - INWESTYCJA W NIERUCHOMOŚCI
I'm sorry for the sudden phone call. My name is Suzuki with Next Estate.
Przepraszam, że zawracam głowę. Jestem Suzuki z firmy Next Estate.
I'm calling today about some newly built investment properties.
Chciałem poinformować o naszych nowych inwestycjach.
You screwed it up, so stop hanging around on the line!
Skopałeś, przestań się obijać!
I told you, once one hangs up, you call the next within five seconds!
Mówiłem, pięć sekund na rozpoczęcie nowej rozmowy!
Idiot! I told you a million times! Do you want to keep getting hit?
I to milion razy, durniu! Chcesz znowu oberwać w łeb?
I'm sorry!
Przepraszam!
Hey, moron!
Baranie!
Would you sit like that if the person was in front of you?
Siedziałbyś tak, mając rozmówcę przed sobą?
You're not believable, because you're not acting like the person was right here!
Nikt ci nie wierzy, bo nie zachowujesz się jak w rozmowie!
This was supposed to be where the money transfer scam happens.
Mieliśmy robić przekręty na przelewy.
But instead they've been making us call people about investment properties.
Zamiast tego kazali nam proponować ludziom inwestycje.
I don't get it.
Nie łapię.
The goal of this training is to get addresses to send materials to!
Celem szkolenia jest zdobycie adresów, na które wyślemy materiały.
Keep on calling until you hook one!
Dzwońcie, aż ktoś się złapie!
Stop lounging around!
Nie obijać się!
-Don't take your hands off the phone! -I'm sorry.
- Bierz tę słuchawkę! - Przepraszam.
Even if each call takes five minutes, that's 36 calls in three hours!
Nawet jak rozmowa zajmie wam pięć minut, w trzy godziny odbędziecie ich 36.
Anyone who does less than that, sits on the floor this afternoon!
Kto nie wyrobi takiej normy, spędzi popołudnie na podłodze!
What are you doing out of your seat?
Czego wstajesz?
If you need to piss, you can piss yourself in your chair!
Jak chcesz szczać, to lej pod siebie!
The morning section is over. Good work!
Koniec porannej sekcji. Dobra robota!
-Good work.
- Dobra robota.
Huh?
Co?
-Here. -Thanks.
- Mam ogień. - Dzięki.
Thanks.
Dziękuję.
This is really rough.
Ciężka robota.
That slap this morning was crazy.
Porządnie ci przywalił.
It still hurts. I'm Seimiya.
Dalej mnie boli. Jestem Seimiya.
I'm Kusano.
Kusano.
-Why are you here? -I saw the ad in a magazine.
- Co tu robisz? - Widziałem ogłoszenie w gazecie.
-Ad? -Wait, you didn't?
- Ogłoszenie? - A ty nie?
Someone told me about it.
Znajomy mi powiedział.
"Operations department. 300,000 a month guaranteed.
„Dział operacyjny, 300 000 miesięcznie.
Transportation fees included."
Zapewniamy transport”.
I knew it would be hard, but I wasn't expecting this.
Wiedziałem, że lekko nie będzie, ale bez przesady.
Look. He's cute, right?
Słodki chłopak, nie?
He's almost four.
Zaraz skończy cztery lata.
I came because I need to find a good job for his sake.
To dla niego szukałem dobrej pracy.
He doesn't know.
On nic nie wie.
No one but me knows that this is where the scams take place.
Tylko ja wiem, że chodzi o przekręty.
I'm disappointed in you clowns. You think you can rest all day?
Rozczarowujecie mnie, pajace. Chcecie tak cały dzień odpoczywać?
We start again in five. I want to see you in your seats ten minutes ahead of time!
Koniec przerwy za pięć minut. Macie być dziesięć minut przed czasem!
On the first day of training, five people quit.
Pierwszego dnia zrezygnowało pięć osób.
HIGASHI HOSPITAL
SZPITAL HIGASHI
-It's full. -Oh, no.
- Ale kolejka. - O nie.
-Please. -Thank you very much.
- Proszę. - Dziękuję.
-Hello. -It's me.
- Halo? - To ja.
Yamada-san.
Pan Yamada.
Have you heard anything from Shotaro?
Shotaro się odzywał?
No, nothing.
Nie.
You sure? You better not be lying to me.
Na pewno? Tylko bez ściemy mi tu.
Hey!
Chłopcze!
-You shouldn't make the elderly wait! -What?
- Nie każ starszym czekać! - Co?
It's nothing.
Nic takiego.
Hurry it up!
Pospiesz się!
These hard seats are hurting my back!
W krzyżu mnie łupie od tych siedzeń!
-What the hell are you talking about? -I'm sorry, right now, I...
- O czym ty mówisz? - Przepraszam, właśnie...
What?
Co?
I'm sorry.
Przepraszam.
Really, I promise, I haven't heard anything from Shotaro.
Przysięgam, Shotaro się nie odzywał.
And... um...
Poza tym...
What is it?
Tak?
I'm doing training at that place.
Poszedłem na to szkolenie.
Who was it that wanted me? Is it Dokugawa, the manager?
Komu na mnie zależało? Dokugawie, temu kierownikowi?
Oh, that?
O to chodzi.
I know! He must have bedsores on his ass!
Wiem! Pewnie ma odleżyny na tyłku!
I'm sorry, what was that?
Co takiego?
So that's the deal.
Posłuchaj.
If you hear from Shotaro, tell me immediately.
Jeśli Shotaro się odezwie, daj mi znać.
I'm going to be sick if we have to wait any longer. Aren't we here to get better?
Zaraz się porzygam. Mieli nas tu leczyć.
So, how is he doing?
Jak się trzyma?
He's doing well. He's talking a lot.
Dobrze. Dużo rozmawiamy.
-Even about the cancer? -He doesn't want to talk about that.
- O raku też? - Nie chce o tym mówić.
It was so sudden, he probably hasn't come to terms with it yet.
Pewnie się jeszcze z tym nie pogodził.
Yeah. That makes sense.
To ma sens.
-Misaki. You're here. -Yo!
- Jesteś, Misaki. - Cześć.
She brought some food. Did you eat?
Przyniosła nam jedzenie. Jadłeś?
I'm not hungry.
Nie jestem głodny.
-Did you catch a cold? -No.
- Przeziębiłeś się? - Nie.
I went to the home helper interview Misaki told me about.
Byłam na tej rozmowie o pracę, o której mówiła Misaki.
They're short-staffed so they want me to start right away. What about you?
Brakuje im pracowników, mogę zaczynać od zaraz. A co u ciebie?
I got the job.
Dostałem pracę.
I have to do some training, but it's a sure thing.
Przede mną szkolenie, ale to pewniak.
-No way! What kind of job? -Investment properties, stuff like that.
- No co ty! Co to za praca? - Inwestycje i nieruchomości.
So it's like your last job. That's great news!
Jak poprzednia. Wspaniale!
-I'm so glad! -Right, Sachiko? Your son's pretty cool!
- Ale się cieszę. - Masz wspaniałego syna.
If you're not going to work, then get out of here!
Jak nie chcesz pracować, to wypad mi stąd!
Are you gonna work?
Weźmiesz się do roboty?
THIRD DAY OF TRAINING
TRZECI DZIEŃ SZKOLENIA
I'm calling you about an investment property opportunity. Yes.
Dzwonię w sprawie inwestycji.
No, I... Please, if I could just take a moment to talk.
Zajmę tylko chwilę.
Where's your ambition?
Gdzie twoje ambicje?
You need to put your whole heart into it! Your spirit!
Włóż w to serce! I duszę!
Or would you prefer to be thrown out like that punk just now?
Może mam cię wywalić jak tego śmiecia?
-Actually... -What?
- Właściwie... - Co?
Do I have to follow the script exactly?
Muszę się trzymać scenariusza?
-What do you mean? -I did operations at my last job.
- Że co? - Robiłem w tej branży.
-So... -"So"? So you think you can do better?
- Więc... - Sądzisz, że znasz się na tym lepiej?
Fine. If you can keep the person on the line, you can say what you want.
Spoko. Dopóki utrzymasz rozmówcę, rób, co chcesz.
-Excuse me... -What?
- Przepraszam... - Czego?
Sorry, what are the materials we're going to send to the customers like?
Jakie materiały będziemy wysyłać?
It's hard to do this without seeing them first.
Ciężko je opisać, skoro ich nie widziałem.
You bring up a good point.
Słuszna uwaga.
-Well... -Don't worry about it.
- Cóż... - Nie przejmuj się.
The materials and the property don't even exist.
Nie ma ani żadnych materiałów, ani inwestycji.
What?
Co?
Don't look at me like that!
Nie gap się tak na mnie!
You trying to say that I wasted your time?
Co, zmarnowałem twój czas?
No!
Nie!
Let me take this opportunity to explain something.
Coś wam wyjaśnię.
Like I said, this work is fake.
Ta fucha to lewizna.
Even if you succeed, there isn't a cent of profit in it.
Nie przyniesie nikomu ani grosza.
However, if you can clear this, you won't be disappointed.
Ale jeśli osiągniecie cel, nie pożałujecie.
Never mind 300,000 a month!
Walić te 300 koła!
If you're good, you can make ten million a month!
Możecie zarobić nawet dziesięć baniek.
If you want to get there, then start making some damn calls!
Jeśli chcecie zobaczyć taką sumę, bierzcie się za rozmowy.
I'll hit anyone who takes their hand off the phone.
Odłóżcie słuchawkę, a dostaniecie po pysku.
-Got it? -Yes, sir!
- Zrozumiano? - Tak jest!
You can make ten million at the actual job.
W tej pracy można zarobić dziesięć milionów.
If what Dokugawa said is true, I may be able to pay my dad's treatment costs.
Jeśli to prawda, opłacę leczenie taty.
First, I need to survive the training.
Ale najpierw muszę przetrwać szkolenie.
FIFTH DAY OF TRAINING
PIĄTY DZIEŃ SZKOLENIA
Seats opened up when people quit because of Dokugawa's harsh treatment.
Wolnych miejsc było coraz więcej. Ludzie nie wytrzymywali presji.
I'm calling today about some newly built investment properties.
Chciałbym opowiedzieć o nowej inwestycji.
Of course. Please don't worry. You can say no at any time.
Oczywiście, może pani w każdej chwili się wycofać.
I see.
Rozumiem.
Well, if there are any other opportunities, I'll call again. Thank you.
Zadzwonię, jeśli pojawią się inne opcje.
-You almost had them. -I'm sorry.
- Prawie ci się udało. - Przykro mi.
I'll show you. You be the old lady.
Pokażę ci. Odegrasz staruszkę.
Hello. I'm sorry for the sudden call.
Dzień dobry, przepraszam, że przeszkadzam.
My name is Suzuki with Next Estate.
Jestem Suzuki z firmy Next Estate.
I'm calling today to tell you about some investment properties.
Chciałbym przedstawić pani możliwość inwestycji.
No, thank you.
Nie, dziękuję.
We have a variety of plans that require very little upfront
Mamy wiele planów inwestycyjnych. Dzięki niskim nakładom
and which allow you to manage your assets at negative interest rates--
zarządzanie przy ujemnym oprocentowaniu...
No, thank--
Nie, dziękuję...
We have plans that require very little upfront.
Nie wymagamy wysokich nakładów.
I would love to help you find a plan that meets your unique needs,
Pomogę pani dopasować plan do pani potrzeb.
so could you kindly tell me your address so I can send some materials?
Proszę mi tylko podać adres, a prześlę wszelkie materiały.
Amazing.
Niesamowite.
Do whatever it takes to get them to give you their address.
Wszystko, by zdobyć te adresy.
-If you don't, I'll kill you. Got it? -Yes, sir.
- Inaczej was pozabijam. Jasne? - Tak jest.
In that call, Dokugawa used two techniques.
Dokugawa użył dwóch technik.
The first was to overwhelm the person by aggressively talking over them.
Po pierwsze, stłamsił rozmówcę, agresywnie mu przerywając.
The second was to repeat what he said over and over.
Po drugie, powtarzał w kółko to samo.
We have a variety of plans that require very little upfront.
Nie wymagamy wysokich nakładów.
I worked tirelessly to learn how to do it myself.
Z całych sił próbowałem się tego nauczyć.
Third city district, street two, number 18.
Trzecia dzielnica, ulica druga, numer 18.
SEVENTH DAY OF TRAINING
SIÓDMY DZIEŃ SZKOLENIA
Thank you. I'll send you the materials right away.
Dziękuję, niezwłocznie prześlę materiały.
Yes. I hope you'll look them over.
Proszę je spokojnie przejrzeć.
Yes. Thank you very much.
Bardzo dziękuję.
-I got it. -Yes! Good job, you little punk!
- Mam. - Dobra robota, gnojku!
Look here!
Proszę!
The reward is 10,000 yen for getting all the way to the end.
Oto 10 000 jenów za doprowadzenie sprawy do końca.
Has this lit a fire under you punks? Here!
Może to was zmotywuje, gnojki. Proszę.
-Keep going until the end! -Yes, sir!
- Nie przestawać! - Tak jest!
Good job.
Dobra robota.
No matter how much I'm praised, my destination is the same...
Ile by mnie nie chwalili, czeka mnie to samo.
You should drink some water.
Napij się wody.
Misaki?
Misaki?
Makoto! Help me out.
Makoto! Pomóż mi.
-Makoto! -Whoa, you're wasted!
- Makoto! - Ale się spiłaś.
We were having some drinks, and things got crazy.
Wyskoczyłyśmy na drinka i trochę przesadziłyśmy.
Shotaro still hasn't come back.
Shotaro nadal nie wrócił.
-Let's get her back home. -Okay.
- Odprowadźmy ją do domu. - Jasne.
Where in the world did Shotaro go?
Gdzie jest Shotaro?
He was talking about some sketchy job. Does it have to do with that?
Mówił o jakiejś podejrzanej robocie. Może to o nią chodzi?
He'll show up sooner or later.
W końcu się zjawi.
By the way, how did that thing go?
A jak ci poszło?
-Your job training. -Training?
- Szkolenie. - Szkolenie?
Yeah.
No.
Yeah. It was okay.
Całkiem nieźle.
Really? I'm rooting for you.
Tak? Trzymam kciuki.
-Hey, Misaki. -Yeah?
- Misaki. - Tak?
What if... And this is purely hypothetical...
A gdybym, tak czysto hipotetycznie,
-My job was-- -Let go of me!
- w pracy... - Puśćcie mnie!
Shut up and bring that idiot back to me!
Przyprowadźcie mi tego idiotę!
Hey, it's okay. Calm down. Let's get you home.
Spokojnie. Odprowadzę cię do domu.
LAST DAY OF TRAINING
OSTATNI DZIEŃ SZKOLENIA
-Sagawa! -Here!
- Sagawa! - Obecny!
-Seimiya!
- Seimiya!
-Goriki! -Here!
- Goriki! - Obecny!
-Kurusu! -Here.
- Kurusu! - Obecny.
-Mori!
- Mori!
You guys did a good job.
Dobra robota.
Good work making it to the last day of training.
Dotrwaliście do ostatniego dnia szkolenia.
There was one moron who didn't even succeed once, but...
Jeden jełop nie zdobył żadnego adresu...
it took real guts to survive my training and make it to the end.
ale żeby przetrwać moje szkolenie, trzeba mieć jaja.
On the last day of training, we're going for a drive.
Dziś wybierzemy się na przejażdżkę.
Think of it as a little field trip.
Potraktujcie to jak wycieczkę.
Take a piss first if you need to. Got it?
Idźcie się odlać, jak trzeba.
-Yes. -Yes, sir.
- Jasne. - Tak jest.
I was this close!
Tyle mi brakowało!
Do any of you golf?
Gracie w golfa?
That's not a surprise.
Nic dziwnego.
We're not here to play. We can't even get in.
Nie przyszliśmy tu grać. Nawet nas nie wpuszczą.
I want you to burn this image into your eyes.
Ale zapamiętajcie sobie ten widok.
This golf course was built in 1988. Right in the middle of the bubble.
Pole zbudowano w 1988 roku, w samym środku bańki.
-You guys know the bubble economy, right? -Yes.
- Znacie tę koncepcję? - Tak.
This course is members-only.
Wstęp mają tylko członkowie.
So only members and the people they bring can play.
Oni i ich goście.
The membership fee is 30 million yen.
Członkostwo kosztuje 30 milionów jenów.
The average member's age is 68.
Średni wiek członka to 68 lat.
Any thoughts?
Jakieś uwagi?
I hope I can live the same way when I'm old.
Też chciałbym tak kiedyś żyć.
They're really going all out so that these old folks can have fun.
Robią wszystko, żeby dziadkowie się bawili.
It costs a lot of money to maintain the green and keep it that color.
Utrzymanie takiego trawnika sporo kosztuje.
Huh. You know a lot.
Sporo o tym wiesz.
My parents were landscape architects, but lost the business when I was a kid.
Rodzice projektowali krajobrazy,
All right, off to the next spot! Come on. Come on.
Ruszamy dalej. W drogę.
-I'm no good in the morning. -Right?
- Nigdy rano nie mam siły. - Prawda?
I was really terrible today!
Okropnie pływałem.
Watch closely. Observe everything you see.
Obserwujcie wszystko dokładnie.
Seimiya, what do you think the average age of that group is?
Seimiya, jaka jest średnia wieku?
Somewhere in the 40s or 50s?
Jakieś 40 albo 50 lat?
You fat-ass! I told you to look closely!
Przyjrzyj się dokładnie, grubasie!
They're the same as most of you. In their 20s and 30s.
Są w waszym wieku. Przed 30.
What?
Co?
Living in poverty has aged them.
Bieda postarza.
The old folks we saw earlier seem a lot more youthful than this lot.
Już tamci dziadkowie mieli więcej energii.
I wonder if I'll end up like those worn out guys.
Boję się, że skończę jak oni.
I want to become a rich old man, too.
Też chciałbym być bogaty na starość.
Do you know what this place used to be?
Wiecie, co tu kiedyś było?
I looked up the address, and it used to be an IT start-up company.
Sprawdziłem adres. Start-up informatyczny.
What about it?
Co z tego?
Some people our age tried to make their own way, and then they failed.
Nasi rówieśnicy próbowali swoich sił, ale im się nie powiodło.
It's a graveyard for the dreams of the young.
To cmentarzysko marzeń młodych ludzi.
No matter how hard you work, you get used up or crushed.
Choćbyście wypruwali sobie żyły, kończycie bez sił.
-What are you punks lounging around for? -Sorry!
- Czemu się obijacie? - Przepraszam!
Where are your manners?
Gdzie wasze maniery?
Hello!
Dzień dobry!
I don't like these formal situations.
Nie lubię oficjalnych rozmów.
Sit down. Relax.
Usiądźcie.
It's okay, sit down. Sit.
Spokojnie, usiądźcie.
-He's telling you to sit! -Sorry.
- Kazał wam usiąść! - Przepraszam.
My name is Kanbe.
Nazywam się Kanbe.
I'm in charge of this office and go around to a few others.
Zarządzam tym biurem i kilkoma innymi.
I'm here to explain to you what your true jobs will be from now on.
Opowiem wam, na czym ma polegać wasza praca.
I'm going to be straight with you.
Nie będę owijał w bawełnę.
The training you went through
Na szkoleniu chcieliśmy zobaczyć,
was all a test to see if you're fit to work the money transfer scam.
czy poradzicie sobie z przekrętem na przelew.
-"Money transfer scam"? -That's right.
- „Przekrętem na przelew”? - Tak.
From now on, you will become players who make phone calls to our targets.
Od tej pory będziecie dzwonić do naszych celów.
Of course, we're not going to force you. If you want, you can leave right now.
Nie będziemy was zmuszać. Możecie odejść, jeśli chcecie.
However...
Jednakże...
if you tell anyone about this...
jeśli komuś o tym powiecie...
Damn.
Rety.
You'll become another page in our diary.
Dostaniecie swoją własną stronę.
-Is this a threat? -What did you say?
- Grozi nam pan? - Coś ty powiedział?
I'm sorry.
Przepraszam.
There's a lot I'm about to tell you.
Mam wam sporo do powiedzenia.
After you listen and think it over, I want you to decide
Później wszystko przemyślicie i podejmiecie decyzję,
whether you're in or not. Do you understand?
czy w to wchodzicie. Zrozumiano?